Guide to the F. Tom Humphrey Photographs Collection 1908-1946
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
F. Tom Humphrey Photographs Collection
1908-1946
1941-1945
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library
Coll 19
Humphrey, F. Tom
114 photographic prints b&w
2 photomechanical prints color, mounted
3 film negatives b&w
Includes one group of aviation-related images, which emphasizes the airplanes of World War II, and a second group of photographs related to the shipyards of the Vancouver-Portland area, also during World War II. Several images document a visit by Henry J. Kaiser to the Kaiser Company shipyards in Vancouver, Washington.
Biographical Note
F. Tom Humphrey (1896-1971) was an editor at the Oregon Journal and Oregon City Enterprise newspapers. Born in Missouri, he attended Central College in Fayette, Missouri, and Colorado State College, before graduating from the School of Aeronautics at the University of California. During World War I he served in the Army as an Air Corps pursuit pilot and instructor. After the war, he worked for several newspapers in California and Colorado before joining the staff of the Oregon Journal l in 1937. During World War II, Humphrey took a leave of absence from the newspaper to serve as area director for the President's Committee for Congested Production Areas (CCPA) monitoring war production. Later he moved to the CCPA national office in Washington, D.C., then joined the Aircraft Industries Association of America as public relations counsel. In 1946, Humphrey returned to the Oregon Journal as associate editor of the editorial page, becoming editor in 1951. He retired from the newspaper in 1962. Humphrey was active in prison and parole reform and civic improvements, including the Memorial Coliseum, the rebuilt Morrison Bridge and the new zoo in Portland. He was an organizer and charter board member of the United Fund and a member of many civic organizations. He served twice on the Governor's Committee on Parole and Probation.
The photographs that make up this collection were assembled by Tom Humphrey in the course of his newspaper and public relations work. The larger series is aviation-related, emphasizing the airplanes of World War II. Also included are several images of a 1928 airplane crash near Salem. The other series is related to the shipyards of the Vancouver-Portland area, again during World War II. Several images document a visit by Henry J. Kaiser to the Kaiser Company shipyards in Vancouver, Washington, including a ship launching and several banquets. Some images are oversize and have been mounted, apparently for framing. The collection also includes a folder of background materials and associated papers.
The collection is organized into three series:
Series A: Background/Associated Papers, 1937-1971
Series B: Aviation, 1908-1946
Series C: Ships and Shipbuilding, 1926-1945
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of F. Tom Humphrey, 1966.
The Oregon Historical Society Research Library holds extensive collections on aviation and shipbuilding that may be accessed through the on-line catalog.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Kaiser, Henry J., 1880-; Jones, L.Q.
Buckler-Chapman Company; Henry J. Kaiser Company; Aeronautical Chamber of Commerce of America; Aircraft Industries Association of America; Boeing Aircraft Company; Curtiss-Wright Corporation; Douglas Aircraft Company; Glenn L. Martin Company; International News Service; North American Aviation, inc.; Pacific & Atlantic Photos, inc.; Photo-Art Commercial Studios; Republic Aviation Corporation; United States. Army Air Force; United States. Navy
Aeronautics; Airplanes; Banquets--1940-1950; Shipbuilding industry--Washington (State)--Vancouver; Ships
Oregon; Washington (State); Photographs; Military; Transportation
Photographic prints; Photomechanical prints; Film negatives
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Background/Associated Papers, 1937-1971; Series A; 1 folder
  - News clippings: Salem, Or., airplane crash, 1928; Humphrey's obituary, 1971 (Box-folder 1/0)
  - Letter to W.C. Crawford of Rose City Brewing Co., Portland, Or., from Pacific Chemical Laboratories, San Francisco, re. testing of beer samples, July 12, 1937 (Box-folder 1/0)
  - Envelope from "Flying Family" jig-saw puzzle (advertising premium from Cocomalt) featuring the George R. Hutchinson family's feats, circa1940, with related print-outs from the World Wide Web (2004) (Box-folder 1/0)
- Aviation, 1908-1946; Series B; 70 items
  The folders are arranged alphabetically by airplane manufacturers and organizations, followed by unidentified aircraft, then an airplane crash at Salem, Or., and finally flyers and other people related to the aircraft industry.
  - AEA (Aerial Experimental Association), 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Testing airplanes: The Loon, Red Wing, and Silver Dart.
  - Boeing, circa 1929-circa 1943 (Box-folder 1/2, Box-folder Over B-1/1)
  - Bristol Airplane, circa1910-circa 1918 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Caproni, 1920 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Curtiss, 1914-1941 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Douglas Aircraft, 1941 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Grumman, circa 1941 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Lockheed, circa 1941-1946 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Martin, 1918-1943 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Military aircraft, U.S. and foreign, circa 1917-1944 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Military aircraft, U.S., circa 1940-circa 1946 (Box-folder Over B-1/2)
  - North American, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Republic Aviation, 1941 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Ryan, 1941 (Box-folder Over A/1)
  - Unidentified aircraft and manufacturing plant, circa 1915-1928 (Box-folder 1/13, Box-folder Over A/2)
  - Unidentified biplane, circa 1910 (Box-folder Over B-1/3)
  - Bodeker-Sloper airplane crash, near Salem, Or., 1928 Mar. 1 (Box-folder 1/14)
    Everett Bodeker, flying instructor, and J. Dare Sloper, student, were killed in crash of Curtiss plane
  - People, circa 1930-circa 1940 (Box-folder 1/15)
    Identified people: Mr. Bailey, Capt. Farley, Dorothy Hester, Mark Jones, Mr. Meadows, Kyle Rose, and Ray Charnhals.
- Ships and Shipbuilding, 1926-1945; 1942-1945; Series C; 46 items
  - Military ships, 1926-1945 (Box-folder 1/16)
    Includes mostly unidentified ships and a view of the U.S. landing on Okinawa, April 20, 1945. Identified ship is aircraft carrier Lexington, unable to leave shipyard at Quincy, Mass., until Fore River Channel could be deepened, Mar. 23, 1926
  - Shipyards, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1/17)
    Includes construction of dormitory at Kaiser Shipyard, Vancouver, Wash., 1942 June. Other images are unidentified but are probably of Kaiser shipyards at Vancouver, Wash., (and possibly Portland, Or.), as well as company personnel.
  - Shipyard banquets, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1/18)
    Kaiser Shipyards at Vancouver, Wash. (and possibly Portland, Or.)
  - Ship launching ceremonies, circa 1942-circa 1944 (Box-folder 1/19)
    Images at Kaiser Shipyard, Vancouver, Wash., document ships, shipyards, officials, guests and workers. Identified people include Henry J. Kaiser; John Hallett, general superintendent of the Vancouver shipyards; and Charles Sprague, Oregon governor.